Matthew Rees

Applied Ecologist

Curriculum Vitae January 2021 **♀** School of Biosciences, University of Melbourne

matthewreesearch.com

+61 412 560 534

matt.wayne.rees@gmail.com

@matt_w_reesmatt-w-reesin matthew-w-rees

Profile

I use quantitative methods to improve monitoring, management and decision-making around invasive species. I specialise in modelling population dynamics and species interactions using hierarchical models, as well as structured decision-making methods to prioritise actions and policies. I have extensive fieldwork experience, leading teams in remote conditions and hold a manual drivers licence, 4WD and first aid training. Working on-ground, alongside stakeholders motivates me to consider landscape context as well as feasibility and socio-economic constraints. I am passionate about applying newly developed statistical methods to real-world datasets, as well as conducting transparent and collaborative science. I am currently finishing up my PhD with the *Quantitative and Applied Ecology group* while tackling the occasional, related contracting job.

Education

2017-present PhD (Conservation Biology)
Interactions between invasive predators and native prey

2013-2016
Bachelor of Environmental Science (1st class Honours)
Prioritising invasive animal management in the Lake Eyre Basin, Australia

Queensland University of Technology

Professional Experience

2019-2020	Ecologist (private contractor)	Winda-mara Aboriginal Corporation, Treetec	
	Training Indigenous rangers in fauna monitoring protocols and grant writing		
2020-2020	Research assistant Designing fox density field surveys	University of Melbourne	
2018-2020	Demonstrator Conservation Biology, Environmental Risk Assessment subjects	University of Melbourne	

Publications

Peer-reviewed

- 1. **MW Rees**, J Carwardine, A Reeson and J Firn (2020). Rapidly assessing cobenefits to advance threat-management alliances. *Conservation Biology*. https://doi.org/10.1111/cobi.13490
- 2. **MW Rees**, JH Pascoe, BA Wintle, M Le Pla, EK Birnbaum and BA Hradsky (2019). Unexpectedly high densities of feral cats in a rugged temperate forest. *Biological Conservation*, 239, 108287. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2019. 108287

In peer-review

- 1. H Davies, Tiwi Land Rangers, **MW Rees**, D Stokeld, A Miller, G Gillespie and B Murphy. Variation in feral cat density between two large adjacent islands in Australia's monsoon tropics.
- 2. M Le Pla, EK Birnbaum, **MW Rees**, BA Hradsky, AR Weeks, A Van Rooyen and JH Pascoe. Genetic sampling and an activity index indicate contrasting lethal control outcomes.
- 3. A Stobo-Wilson... **MW Rees**... Sharing meals: predation on Australian mammals by the introduced European red fox compounds and complements predation by feral cats.
- 4. A Stobo-Wilson... **MW Rees**... Reptiles as food: predation of Australian reptiles by introduced red foxes compounds and complements predation by cats.
- 5. A Stobo-Wilson... **MW Rees**... Compounding and complementary carnivores: Australian bird species eaten by the introduced European red fox Vulpes vulpes and domestic cat Felis catus
- 6. A Stobo-Wilson... **MW Rees**... Counting the bodies: the numbers of, and spatial variation in, Australian reptiles, birds and mammals killed by two introduced predators.

Reports

1. MW Rees (2020). Monitoring and managing critical weight range mammals in the indigenous protected areas of the world heritage Budj Bim cultural landscape. A report prepared for the Victorian Government, Department of Environment, Land, Water and Planning.

Grants and awards

2020	University of Melbourne, School of Biosciences, Jasper Loftus-Hills award	\$2.25K
2020	University of Melbourne, School of Biosciences, travel grant	\$2K
2020	Ecological Society of Australia, Hoslworth research endowment	\$7.5K
2019	Ecological Society of Australia, Hoslworth research endowment	\$6.75K
2018	Conservation Ecology Centre student scholarship	\$5K
2017	Victorian Environmental Assesment Council, Bill Borthwick scholarship	\$2K
2017	Victorian Government, Parks Victoria research partners program (co-investigator)	\$20K
2017	Victorian Government, Department of Land, Environment, Land, Water and Planning research grant	\$15K
2017	Victorian Government, Department of Land, Environment, Land, Water and Planning, PhD top-up scholarship	\$15K
2017	Australian federal government, RTP PhD scholarship	\$98K
2016	Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation, honours top-up scholarship	\$10K
2015	University of Wollongong, undergraduate research scholarship	\$7.2K

Presentations

- ➤ Australian Wildlife Management Society (virtual), December 2020. Drivers of feral cat density and spatio-temporal behaviour
- ➤ Ecological Society of Australia (virtual), December 2020. Drivers of feral cat density and spatio-temporal behaviour.
- ➤ Australian Mammal Society (virtual), November 2020. Drivers of feral cat density and spatio-temporal behaviour.
- ➤ International Statistical Ecology Conference (virtual), June 2020. Using spatial mark-resight and GAMs to infer predator interactions.
- ➤ Guest lecture, University of Melbourne, Australian Wildlife Biology, May 2020, Invasive mammals in Australia.
- ➤ Ecological Society of Australia, Launceston, November 2019, Does fox control increase feral cat population density?
- ➤ Wimmera Biodiversity Seminar, Rupanyup, September 2019, Monitoring predators and prey in south-west VIC.
- ➤ Otway Threatened Species Forum, Geelong, August 2019, Monitoring predators and prey in the Otways .
- ➤ Victorian Biodiversity Conference, Melbourne, February 2019, Prioritising invasive animal management in the Lake Eyre Basin to benefit both threatened species and agriculture.
- ➤ Ecological Society of Australia, Brisbane, November 2018, Modelling invasive predator density in mesic forests.
- ➤ Otway Threatened Species Forum, Geelong, August 2018, How many feral cats are in the Otway Ranges?
- ➤ Mathematics of Biological Systems Symposium, Melbourne, April 2018, *Integrating co-benefits into the cost-effective prioritisation of conservation strategies*.
- ➤ Victorian Biodiversity Conference, Melbourne, February 2018, How many cats are in the Otways?
- ➤ Environmental Institute of Australia & New Zealand conference, Brisbane, August 2017, Building alliances between the agriculture and conservation sectors.

Media

09/12/2019	Radio interview	ABC Melbourne	Invasive predators interactions
20/09/2019	Television segment feature	TF1 French National News	Invasive animals in Australia
08/08/2019	Radio interview	3AW	Invasive predators in south-west VIC
08/08/2019	Newspaper article (front page)	Geelong Advertiser	Invasive predators in south-west VIC
07/08/2019	Radio interview	ABC South West Victoria	Invasive predators in south-west VIC
13/03/2019	Newspaper article	Colac Herald	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
11/03/2019	Radio interview	ABC Melbourne	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
11/03/2019	Live TV interview	ABC news	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
10/03/2019	Online news article	ABC news	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges
10/03/2019	Radio interview	ABC Ballarat	Feral cat density in the Otway Ranges

Service

- ➤ Peer-reviewer (Conservation Biology, Wildlife Research, Austral Ecology, Australian Mammalogy)
- ➤ Treasurer, BioSciences Postgraduate Society (2019-2020)
- ➤ Coding club and social media contributor with QAECO lab group
- ➤ Ecological Society of Australia award judging panel (2020)